A Finding Aid to the Arthur B. Carles papers, 1912-1983, in the Archives of American Art aaa.carlarth
Archives of American Art
Arthur B. Carles papers
1912-1983
aaa.carlarth
Archives of American Art
0.6 Linear feet
The papers of Philadelphia painter Arthur B. Carles measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1912 to 1983. Found are biographical materials, correspondence, writings and notes, personal business records, printed materials, and photographs.
Carles, Arthur B., 1882-1952
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 1 series. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Series 1: Arthur B. Carles papers, 1912-1983 (0.6 linear feet; Box 1-2, MGP 3)
Biographical/Historical note
Arthur B. Carles (1882-1952) was a painter and art instructor active in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
Born in 1882 in Philadelphia, Arthur B. Carles studied at the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts from 1900-1907. There he studied with Thomas Pollock Anshutz, Hugh Breckenridge, Henry McCarter, Cecilia Beaux, and William Merritt Chase. Carles traveled to France in 1907 and stayed until 1910, becoming close friends with John Marin and Eduard Steichen. He displayed his work in the Salon d'Automne of 1908.
Upon Carles' return to Philadelphia, he accepted a position at the Pennsylvania Academy as an instructor of French and American modernism. In 1910 his work was included in the "Younger American Painters" show held at Alfred Stieglitz's New York gallery, 291. Also, Stieglitz gave Carles his first one-man show in 1912. Carles exhibited at the Armory Show of 1913.
Arthur Carles had one daughter, painter Mercedes Matter. He married Carolina Robinson as his second wife in 1972. Later in life, he suffered from alcoholism and had a stroke in 1941 that left him an invalid. Carles died in 1952.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Other Finding Aids note
An inventory of the papers was prepared by art historian Barbara Wolanin and is available by request at the Archives' Washington, DC office. The inventory does not follow the order of the papers as currently arranged, but provides detailed information about items.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of the papers were microfilmed on reels 3667 and 4076. The microfilm is available for interlibrary loan but researchers are advised that the microfilm does not reflect the current order of the papers and may be incomplete.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Arthur B. Carles papers were donated by Sara F. Swanson in 1985. Additional papers were donated by Perry Ottenberg in 1985.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Philadelphia painter Arthur B. Carles measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1912 to 1983. Found are biographical materials, correspondence, writings and notes, personal business records, printed materials, and photographs.
Correspondence is found for Carles and his wife Caroline Robinson Carles and includes letters from Sarah Baker, R. Sturgis Ingersoll, Henry McCarter, John Marin, Leopold Seyffert, Maurice Speiser, Carroll and Henry Tyson, and Franklin Watkins, among others. One diary contains brief entries. Additional writings are by Carles and Perry Ottenberg. Photographs are of Carles, his studio, family and friends, exhibitions, and works of art.
Separated Materials note
Additional papers of the Arthur B. Carles were loaned for microfilming by Steven Casamassima and Perry Ottenberg, and then returned. This material is available on reels 1052, and 4270-4273 and includes correspondence, writings and notes, business material, artwork, photographs, and business records.
Baker, Sarah, 1899-; Carles, Caroline Robinson; Ingersoll, R. Sturgis (Robert Sturgis), b. 1891; Marin, John, 1870-1953; McCarter, Henry, 1866-1942; Ottenberg, Perry, 1924-; Seyffert, Leopold; Speiser, Maurice J., (Maurice Joseph), 1880-; Tyson, Carol; Tyson, Henry; Watkins, Franklin Chenault, 1894-1972; Art, Modern--20th century--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Artists' studios--Photographs; Diaries; Painters--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Painting, Abstract--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Photographs
- Arthur B. Carles papers, 1912-1983; Series 1; 0.6 Linear feet Box 1-2, MGP 3
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials include the marriage certificate and wedding announcement of Carles and Carolina Robinson. Correspondence includes letters from Sarah Baker, R. Sturgis Ingersoll, Henry McCarter, John Marin, Leopold Seyffert, Maurice Speiser, Carroll and Henry Tyson, and Franklin Watkins. Also, there is correspondence for Carolina Robinson Carles. Writings by Carles include two small notebooks, one containing telephone numbers and brief, irregular entries; and photographs of writings. Writings by others are found for Perry Ottenberg. Business records include receipts and a price list. Printed material includes clippings and other printed miscellany. Also found are photographs including photos of Carles, his family and friends (including one of Carles and his daughter Mercedes and Hans Hofmann), exhibitions, and of works of art. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
  - Biographical Material, 1927-circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Correspondence, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, circa 1930s-circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Diary and Notebook, 1927-circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Writings and Notes by Carles, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Writings by Perry Ottenberg, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Business Records, 1934-circa 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Periodicals, 1925; 1912 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Maps, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1910s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1940-1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, Exhibition, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, Carles with Family and Friends, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, Studio, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, Works of Art, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, Installations--Calder Mobile, circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Copyprints, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Negatives, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1920; 6 Glass negatives (Box MGP 3)